<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony for the truth and against deceit and deceivers with a reproof unto those who are not faithful to the truth which they are convinced of / By Stephen Smith.</title>
            <author>Smith, Stephen, 1623-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42476381</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42476381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2256:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony for the truth and against deceit and deceivers with a reproof unto those who are not faithful to the truth which they are convinced of / By Stephen Smith.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Stephen, 1623-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[xxiv], 180 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.], :</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: The 21th day of the 11th moneth, 1667.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Truth --  Quaker authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151357:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY FOR THE TRUTH, And againſt DECEIT and DECEIVERS, WITH A <hi>Reproof</hi> unto thoſe who are not Faithful to the <hi>Truth</hi> which they are convinced of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Stephen Smith.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 26.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee: but they ſhall ſee, and be aſhamed for their Envy at the People.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſe 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lord, thou wilt ordain Peace for us; for thou haſt wrought all our works in us.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1668.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151357:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151357:2"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony for the TRUTH, and againſt <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> with a Reproof unto thoſe who are not faithfull to the Truth which they are Convinced of.</head>
            <p>FOr as much as it hath pleaſed the Lord in his great love and tender mercy to viſit many who have been long covered with Darkneſs, and drawn by the Subtilty of the Serpent, working in a Myſtery within, and without in his Inſtruments, from enjoying that Love and great Riches which is declared of in the Scriptures of Truth, which ſhould be revealed in the latter dayes, in his Everlaſting and Unchangable Covenant; which Promiſe of the Lord many who had true breathing after him, and could not be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with feeding with Swine upon Husks, but truly breathed after Living Refreſhment, and after that Bread which nouriſheth that Birth which is Eternal, and have delighted in the righteous Judgments of the Lord, over the Enemy and Oppreſſor of Mans Soul, through which Judgments the Love of God hath greatly been manifeſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereby brought to the knowledge of his Everlaſting and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable Truth, to the exceeding great refreſhment and ſatisfaction of the Souls of many thouſands, who have earneſtly deſired the ſame before the World and all its glory; and having received the ſame in the Love of it, and known Freedom by it, in the Injoyment of the ſame do meet together, as the manner and practice was of thoſe who lived in the Fear and Dread of the Lord in the Primitive times; ſo now in the pure Fear and Obedience to the juſt and equal requirings of their Creator (whoſe Wayes are Equal, Right and Juſt) meets together to wait on him, to the end they may be refreſhed and fed with the ſame Bread of Life, that ſo the Plant which the Lord hath planted may grow, that ſo they may be changed from glory to glory, till at length they may come to bear the Image of the Heavenly, whereas formerly they have born the Image of the Earthly; and thoſe who ſo meet in the Spirit of Truth, can truely ſay they never waited
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151357:3"/>on the Lord in vain, but do witneſs true refreſhment from the God of Love, whether a word be ſpoken in their Meetings or no; ſo that they can truly ſing in their Spirits of Mercy and of Judgements, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the Lord hath mixed Mercy with Judgments, and hath not executed Judgment without Mercy, in which hath greatly appeared his wonderfull Love to loſt Mankind, of which great and unſpeakable Love, there are this day (to the Glory and Praiſe of his great Name, even from his own Works) thouſands of Living Witneſſes, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds have laid down their Lives in Naſty Holes, and Stinking Priſons, and many have been Baniſhed, and many have ſuffered cruel Mockings, &amp; many thouſands the Spoiling of their Goods, whoſe Righteous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony through the Eternal Spirit of Love and Truth they have glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born in this Day of Gods Power, to the exceeding Comfort and Refreſhment of all that are faithfull Followers of the Lamb, but is, and ſhall be to the aſtoniſhment of all who perſiſt in their Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence againſt the Spirit of Truth, and continue in their Rebellion againſt it, and this righteous Teſtimony, through all who are true Worſhippers in the Spirit and Truth, who are led and guided in all their wayes by the Spirit of truth, being Sons and Daughters of the Living God, ſo greatly beloved by him; ſo that thoſe that touch them in a wrongfull manner do touch the Apple of his Eye, who crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things for his Glory; and though his Mercy is great in not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting Judgement ſpeedily, but gives ſpace and time of Repentance, yet if they mind it not, but let the Day of Gods Love paſs over their heads, that Terrible Voice they ſhall hear; <hi>My Spirit ſhall ſtrive no more,</hi> let Fleſh know that its but Graſs, &amp; when the Spirit of the Lord bloweth upon it, it ſhall fade as a Flower, and that in a moment, when his Anger is kindled, which may be when the Worker of Iniquity is in the height of his vain glory, and greateſt boaſting: ſo as that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Teſtimony (through all who are in the true Innocent Seed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which all the Bleſſings and the Promiſes of the Lord are) doth ſtand as a true Witneſs of the Lords great Love in this day wherein he is making known his great Power againſt all Workers of Iniquity, and unrighteous Actions, and deceitfull Workers, who can feign and flatter with all ſorts of debauched Perſons, and all diſſembling Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, Perſons of unſtable minds, joyning with the cunning, twiſting, twining Serpent, in all its appearances, in their earthly, ſenſual, and devilliſh wiſdom, being in the Adulterous whoriſh ſpirit, degenerated
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151357:3"/>from the Spirit of Truth, holding a Profeſſion of the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with reſpect of Perſons, receiving honour, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving honour, according to the Cuſtoms and vain Traditions of the World, by which means they have no knowledge of that Honour which is from Above: yet notwithſtanding theſe great Abominations which they commit in the ſight of the Lord, and all them which lives in their faithful Teſtimony againſt them, yet they lean upon the Lord, and thinks there ſhall come no evil upon them; but except ſuch do ſpeedily repent, and turn from their Abominations, and bow to the righteous Teſtimony of God in them, which ſhews them the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of their heares, to the end they may above, and before all, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a clean heart, and a right Spirit, that ſo they may be ſingle heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed toward their Creator, and all men; which except that be known, the Lord will ſend a day upon them, wherein ſhall be weeping, and howling, and bitter Lamentation; and their Torment ſhall be ſo great, that in the Morning they ſhall wiſh it were Night, and at Night they ſhall wiſh for Morning, and many ſhall deſire Death rather then Life: So I greatly deſire that all People would mind, in coolneſs, how it ſtands between them and their Creator, and deal impartially with themſelves, for, of a certain, God will not be mocked, but ſuch as they ſow, ſuch they muſt reap: So all mind <hi>the Fear of the Lord, which is to depart from Evil,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Curſe</hi> of the Lord may be done away, and his <hi>Bleſſing</hi> known and received.</p>
            <p>And thoſe that comes amongſt the Poſſeſſors of Truth, who have heard the ſound of it, and ſo a belief is raiſed in their hearts, that God is found by them that diligently ſeek him in the Way of Truth; many there be that are thus perſwaded, and ſo frequent Meetings (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with them that are in the work of Truth) in a bare Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Truth, never throughly given up to the end that Truth may be their <hi>Guide</hi> in all their wayes, but comes and ſits down with ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in their hearts, which they covet to keep, as <hi>Achan</hi> did the goodly Babyloniſh Garment, which was appointed for the Fire; but for ſo doing the Curſe of the Lord followed him, though his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs was a trouble to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for a time, yet at length God made it manifeſt; and ſo will the Lord do thoſe who comes amongſt <hi>Friends</hi> with a reſerve in their hearts; that which is appointed for the Fire, they that covet to keep, notwithſtanding the many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Meetings they come to, and hear their conditions plainly laid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151357:4"/>open to them, yet ſtill conſulting with Fleſh and Blood, which will never yeeld that true obedience ſhould be given to the Lord, ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not amend, but continue in the ſame courſe of life, for not taking heed to the Councel of the Lord, nor giving wholy up to be guided by the Spirit of Truth; ſuch are not in the Way of Truth, but ſit down as dead Branches by thoſe of the Vine; but their Fruit doth manifeſt them: for thoſe that deals ſo deceitfully with their own Hearts, how can it be expected they ſhould be true to others? ſo ſuch becomes an ill ſavour to Truth, as long as they continue ſo, and a burthen and a trouble to them that are in the way of growing in the Truth; but let them know who harden their hearts againſt Reproof, and though they do come amongſt them that lives in the Fear and Dread of the Lord, and ſo meet together that they may receive a continual ſupply of the Bread of Life, and enjoy the Preſence of the Lord; yet their ſo coming with a reſerve in their heart, they cannot profit by it: So at length, ſeeing they cannot bring the Way of the Lord to their way, they begin to grow cold in meeting, and ſo by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees the Enemy draws out the mind, and then gets room for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, and ſo perſwades them to wait no longer, but that all Places are alike: and ſo at length ſome gets into the Maſs-Houſe, with other ſilly People <hi>laden with ſins, ever learning, and never able to come to the Truth;</hi> and begins to perſwade themſelves, (or the Enemy of their Souls perſwades them) that there is little difference in the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Miniſters of Chriſt and Antichriſt; their words, ſay they, are all good, and ſo begins to build <hi>Babel</hi> again, having rejected that Love which did appear for their Everlaſting good, having choſen to pleaſe themſelves in ſome ſmall thing, which they could not part with, though no better then a Meſs of Pottage, for which many have ſold an Eternal inheritance; ſo with <hi>Cain</hi> they are in the Curſe, wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and down in that which is curſed of the Lord, and not beloved of good men; ſo the Lord hath dealt juſtly in making them manifeſt, <hi>They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us,</hi> but their reward will follow them. And many others there be that comes to Meetings, and hears Truth declared often, and confeſſeth its the Truth, but when they ſee, if they come to obey, they muſt take up a Croſs to Fleſh, either in denying to fear man, or elſe hazard of loſing Goods, and ſome their Companions and Acquaintance, (though it may be in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity) and ſuch like Baits the Enemy of mans Soul hath ready, for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151357:4"/>that mind which is willing to catch at them, to ſave that alive which is in the Curſe; ſo ſometimes they come, and ſometimes ſtay away, and then come again, and the Enemy of their Souls gets a wound now and then; but for want of giving up, at length the Enemy begins to be whole again, and ſo the Spirit of the Lord is grieved and quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by degrees, and the Enemy grows ſtronger and ſtronger; and at length he gets theſe Reaſons in the Creature, becauſe the Enemy knows many will not be ſatisfied without ſome plauſible Reaſon; ſo he tells many, why thou art but a poor Creature, or you are but poor Creatures, and what can you do without power? ſo here the willing mind readily catches at this bait: and then when they are asked, why they give not up, O ſay they, we want power, O that I had but power to do ſo and ſo, how joyfull ſhould I be; and ſuch like ſtuff the Enemy furniſheth them withal, who are willing to receive it, and in the mean time ſlights the appearance of Chriſt, (the Light, in whom Power is received) by grieving and quenching his Holy Spirit of Truth, in which is the greateſt manifeſtation of Love that God could beſtow on loſt Mankind, in making manifeſt his Son in their hearts, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming them up unto himſelf, out of their loſt condition, in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Adam</hi> in the fall, up into the Nature of the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> which never fell: but how is this Love of God ſlighted by thoſe who thus wilfully yeelds to the Enemy of their Souls, and rejecting the Lord, who ſearcheth the Heart, and tryeth the Reins, and then ſay they want power; and its true, when people have given themſelves up to the power of the Enemy, whoſe nature is to do all the hurt he can, they may well ſay then they want power to do good, that being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteemed and accounted of as a thing of nought, having caſt behind them the great Love of God in his Son, and embraced ſomething which the Enemy hath ſet before them, as ſome glory in the World, and the like; but as he was alwayes a Lyar, (the Devil) ſo will he be found in this; for inſtead of giving them the glory of the World, he is fitting them for Gods Wrath and Indignation, that ſo when he is caſt out of thoſe of more upright hearts, and more thankfull, that he may poſſeſs thoſe Swiniſh natures, and ſo throw them headlong into a Sea of Deſtruction, with others of the like bad natures, of whom I ſhall ſay ſomething.</p>
            <p>Thoſe are they which have heard and ſeen ſomething of Truth, by reading Books, or ſpeaking with ſome in the Truth, whoſe words
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151357:5"/>being accompanied with power, proceeding from the Spirit of Truth, they not having been able to reſiſt, but ſtanding over them, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onings and reaſoning hath been raiſed in them concerning their build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whether or no they be upon the right Foundation; but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing catch'd too, which ſhews them their conditions ſo plain, that they have no aſſurance of their well-being, but in doubtings, and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and fears, through which ſecretly torment doth ariſe; but their minds being from him that ſhews them their conditions, which, though it be the greateſt Love that God could beſtow on loſt Mankind, yet in that it brings a Croſs to fleſh, ſeeing plainly that if they hearken to it, they muſt forſake all their vain cuſtoms &amp; traditions of the world, with all its Luſts &amp; Vanities; theſe things not agreeing with Fleſh &amp; Blood, with which they are conſulting, the mind being drawn from the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for God in their hearts, by their wilfull yeelding to the Enemy of their Souls, who is alwayes ready with his Baits to betray them who deſires eaſe in the Fleſh, and whoſe minds are out in ſtudying Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to keep them in the ſame, the ſubtil Serpent being here at work, to the end that the Creature may pertake of his Table, for he knows that then they cannot pertake of Gods Table, as the Scriptures of Truth declares; ſo at his Table he hands out curious words, in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and hanging down the head like a Bullruſh, and with feigning and flattering words to all ſorts of Deceitfull Workers, and doth help to turn and wind with all ſorts of Worſhip, which the Beaſtly Nature ſets up, and ſo tells them there is Fleſh as well as Spirit to be ſatisfied, and that they muſt live in ſin, as long as they have a being here; and to others, whoſe natures be inclined to Luſt, he provides plentifull Diſhes for them; and others, who are diſpoſed to Drunkenneſs, he directs them to Companions, and opportunity; and at his Table are variety of Diſhes for the Covetous man, or Proud, High, Heady, Boaſter, Curſer, Ranter, for all ſorts that will come to his Table, he hath curious Diſhes in a plentious manner, and in all theſe he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes content and ſatisfaction; but as he ever was, ſo he is, and ever will be a Lyar; for let thoſe ſpeak who hath fed moſt plentiful at his Table, if ever they were ſatisfied, but that the more they fed the more hungry they were; let all all theſe forementioned, and Gamſters ſpeak for themſelves, and Thieves, and Murtherers, and the like. But in ſome he works more in a Myſtery, and furniſheth his Table with curious words, and ſo feeds them, and decks them; but alwayes at his Table
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151357:5"/>he hath this Diſh for all ſorts of Profeſſors and Prophane, that they muſt live in Sin, in this Life; this is, as it were, a Chain, by which he holds all, that will believe ſo, faſt to his Table; and then let them be as rich as they will, in comprehending, and getting into the Brain-knowledge the Scriptures, and outward Learning, ſo though the work grows ſo high in the Myſtery of Iniquity, that the Enemy of the Soul hath exalted himſelf above all that is called God, and ſo makes a ſhew in fine Words, and in long Prayers, and in curious Arts; yet whilſt he can keep them in his Chain to his Table, if they cannot have eaſe in profeſſing in one Sect, he will give them leave to profeſs in another Sect; and if that will not ſerve he will give them leave to go into the profeſſion of Truth it ſelf; and further, to meet together with them in the Truth, any thing but hearing the Voice of the Son of God, and obeying, which brings to the Table of God, and ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws his Table; to any thing but this his Chain will reach: Now, as to what is before, thoſe that have ſeen ſomething of Truth, and ſome trouble hath by reaſon thereof riſen in them, but for love of a little eaſe to the fleſh, ſuch their minds being out, willingly goes into the Devils Chain, and ſo feeds at his Table, where they are furniſhed with Arguments againſt the Spirit of Truth manifeſted to lead and to guide into all truth, and ſo out of Sin, which is the Devils Chain; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus furniſhed according to their hearts luſts, being in the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Spirit, takes all occaſion to ſpeak evil of the Truth, and them that are in it, who are true worſhippers of the Lord, according to his Will, in Spirit and Truth; ſo the god of the World having blinded their minds, an evil eye gets out, and this watches for the halting of them who are in Truth; and when the juſt hand of God is gone out, in making manifeſt ſome who have been in the profeſſion of Truth, who have hardned their hearts againſt reproof, till at length their hypocriſie and guile is made manifeſt; on which, they hereby take occaſion to ſpeak evil of the Way of the Lord, and them that are in it, the Enemy of their Souls giving them thereby ſome eaſe for the preſent; but it laſts not long, but the Fame of Truth is ſounded in their ears again, by the Witneſs for God within, or elſe from thoſe in whom in dwells without them then the Lamb riſeth, and gives torment again, &amp; their Coverings be too narrow, &amp; will not ſerve them, neither ſhall they; <hi>Wo to the Rebellious Children ſaith the Lord, that take Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, but not of me, and that cover with a covering, but not with my Spirit:</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151357:6"/>So all unrighteous Coverings which people of unſtable minds are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Wo of the Lord is againſt, ſo what will become of them that are under them? O that men would in coolneſs conſider, whoſe day of Gods Viſitation in Love is not paſt, leſt by their often provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he viſits in his great Diſpleaſure, and ſays <hi>My Spirit is weary with ſtriving, it ſhall ſtrive no more:</hi> now for the ſakes of many who have yet true Breathings after Living Refreſhment, and are willing to take up Chriſts Yoke and Burthen, and to follow him that is meek and lowly in heart, that ſo they may find reſt for their Souls; for their ſakes I ſhall give a brief Relation of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and of the Miniſters of Antichriſt: Firſt, The Miniſters of Chriſt muſt know Chriſt, and ſee him, and believe on him, <hi>John</hi> 6.40. But ſome will ſay, Who is there that knows not Chriſt? Doth not all that can read ſee what is writ of him in the Scriptures of Truth? And is not that the Ghriſt which you mean, who ſuffered without the Gates of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and the like? Yes, we do own the ſame Chriſt, and that which the Scriptures do declare of him is true, and we do expect no other; but to know him no further then the report of him, (though that be true) this is but a poor knowledge, which the Workers of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have, of all ſorts, that lives viſibly in groſs and manifeſt Sins; and notwithſtanding that knowledge, yet live and abound in the ſame; ſo that knowledge only (though that, as I have ſaid, be true) is not ſufficient to fit a man to be a Miniſter of Chriſt: But ſaith the diligent Enquirer. What knowledge then is neceſſary for a Miniſter of Chriſt? To know him as he is the Myſtery hid from Ages and Generations, but now is made manifeſt to his Saints: to know what is the Riches of the Glory of this Myſtery among the Gentiles, <hi>which is Chriſt in you the Hope of Glory,</hi> Colloſ. 1.26, 27. To know him as he is a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant given to the People, and a Light to enlighten them, manifeſted within them, to give the knowledge of God; and to know that he is the Light of the World, and how he hath enlightened every man that comes into the World: to know him to be the Word in the Heart and in the Mouth: to know him to be the Reconciler unto God: to know him to be the Anointing, which is true, and teacheth all things: to know him to be the Spirit of Truth, which is manifeſt to lead and to guide into all Truth: to know Chriſts Fleſh, and what it is to each: to know Chriſts Blood, and what it is to drink it: but ſome will ſay, all this may be read in the Scriptures: But by the way,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151357:6"/>thought the words may be read in the Scriptures of Truth, yet the knowledg of the Myſtery which is declared of in thoſe words, is not attainable by reading them: But becauſe ſome are willingly ignorant, and ſo deſires to be, rather then to have true wiſdom in Gods Way. and ſo ſtumbles at all, I ſhall ſay a little concerning ſeeing the Son, which is neceſſary for a Miniſter of Chriſt; Firſt, To ſee him to be the great Love of God manifeſted to convince of Sin: to ſee him to be the wonderfull Power of God, and how that he died, to the end, that whether we ſleep or wake we ſhould live together with him: to ſee him as he was manifeſt to deſtroy the Works of the Devil: to ſee him to be the great Miſtery of Godlineſs, God manifeſt in the Fleſh; and much more might be ſaid of the knowledge and ſight which a true Miniſter of Chriſt hath, but what hath been ſaid is enough to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the truly hungring and thirſting Soul; but the full loaths the Hony comb: But is this all may the upright-hearted ſay? Nay, they that thus have obtained mercy to have the knowledge of what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove declared, muſt receive it in the love of it, and this Love of God thus manifeſted in them they muſt give up to obey, being his Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and Unchangeable Covenant, which is the Key of Knowledge, manifeſted to rend the Vail, and to break the Chain of Darkneſs, and to open the Myſteries of the Scriptures of Truth, and to give the knowledge of God, whom to know is Eternal Life; ſo Iniquity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, and Sin being purged through the knowledge of Chriſt, who is the Power of God, and God known to walk, and to dwell in them through the Son of his Love, who is Gods Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as God hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in you, and walk in you:</hi> The Eye of the Underſtanding being thus opened, and the Revelation of Chriſt being daily witneſſed to fit and to furniſh them with Wiſdom from above, to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon unto all conditions; being thus filled with the Love of God, and his Glorious Appearance, a conſtraint lying upon them, through the Power of God that dwells in them, and from the great Love of God in the ſame, ſuch cannot be ſilent, nor eat their Morſel; alone but the Love of God doth conſtrain them who have Wives, and Children, and Eſtates, and ſeveral others that have no Wives and Children, to leave their Callings, and ſeveral Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and go abroad as Sheep among Wolves, to declare this great and unſpeakable Love, to the end, <hi>That People may be turned from Darkneſs to Light, and from Satans power, to the Power of God,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151357:7"/>that others may partake of the ſame Love of God in his Son Chriſt Jeſus with them: But for this their love, how Barbarouſly and Cruelly they have been uſed, many having finiſhed their Teſtimony in Naſly Holes, and Priſons, and other great Cruelties, which would be too long to relate; ſo theſe thus furniſhed with the Love and Power of God, and being obedient to the ſame, being Learned men in the Book of Life; theſe are not to take with them Scrip nor Purſe, ſo as to be carefull of Earthly things, (but as they have received freely, do mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter freely) but into what houſe they come, where this great Love is anſwered in the ſame Love of God in meaſure, what things ſuch ſet before them, for neceſſity they eat and drink, and the like, ſeeing it comes from their Fathers Love: but when they come into a place and cannot ſee, in the Counſel of the Lord, that that Love is anſwered in which they come, there they cannot receive, though in never ſo much neceſſity. True, ſay ſome, theſe are fit Qualifications for a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt; but be there any ſuch now adayes? How doſt thou know them? Yes, I do teſtifie, as thouſands beſide my ſelf are ready to give the ſame teſtimony, that ſuch Miniſters, qualified, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, there be many in this Day of Gods Power: But how do you know, may ſome ſay? I anſwer, By turning us to the great and unſpeakable Love of God manifeſted in our hearts, which ſhews us our conditions, how it ſtood between us and our Creator, as it had done long before, but we knew not that this was the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Son of his Love, till thoſe who had taſted, handled, ſeen and ſelt the powerfull working thereof told us; but told us alſo, the firſt ſtep muſt be through Judgment; ſo a belief thereof being raiſed, and a clean and a perfect obedience yeelded to it, we in time found its power in us, opening the Eye of our Underſtandings, and revealed the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of Sin; and ſo came the knowledge of the Spirit of Truth to be revealed in us, and by it we had a ſight of the unfruitfull Works of Darkneſs without in his Inſtruments, and the ſight of the Spirit of Truth, and thoſe that were Miniſters of it: But notwithſtanding this Teſtimony, if ſome ſhould be hard to believe, let ſuch deal ſo ingeniouſly with their own Souls, as to go and hear, and try, with a ſingle heart, and hold faſt that which is good; and this is deſired, to the end that others may be partakers of the ſame Love of God, and of their aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their being reconciled unto him through his Son, to whom be glory for ever. Now there being a neceſſity that the Miniſters of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151357:7"/>Chriſt ſhould be qualified, as is before mentioned, the Miniſters of Antichriſt may be eaſily known; but for the ſakes of ſuch aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, I ſhall lay down ſome marks of them: Firſt, They are ſuch who never knew the Son of God in the Everlaſting and Unchangable Covenant manifeſted in them, ſo not learned men in the Book of Life, but are alienated from the Life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, not knowing him manifeſted in them, who is infallible, but in their fallible wiſdom, by the Art of Tongues, gets the Prophets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles words, and ſomething out of Heathen Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and ſo in their vain imaginations patches up an hours Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and ſo for the love they have for their god, which is their Belly, they ſell their Art at as dear a price as they can, for ſeveral hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds by the year, ſome for more, and ſome for leſs, but all as dear as poſſible; as I heard a Prieſt ſay once, if it were not for Tythes who as would ſhould preach for him: but this being ſo well known to all, that its alone for their god, which is their Belly, that their Mouthes is open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there is little need to ſpeak of that, theſe being Sayers, but not Doers, ſo not accepted of God; theſe are they which run and are not ſent, which ſpeaks a divination of their own Brain, ſo not like to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the people, you may read of them at large <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the thirteenth, read the Chapter; from ſuch Prieſts and Prophets as theſe is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs gone forth in all the Land, read <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the twenty third; ſo they are ſufficiently markt out in the Scriptures of Truth. But ſome ſay, we know all the Prieſts now adayes are bad enough, and the ſmootheſt of them preaches for filthy lucre ſake, but they ſpeak good words; ſo we may do as they ſay, and not as they do: O fooliſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is it not becauſe you love ſuch eaſie Prophets, who ſpeaks peace to you in your Sins, that you thus ſpeak? have you not heard what the Scriptures of Truth ſayes? <hi>Do men gather Grapes of therns, or Figs of Thiſtles? By their Fruits you may know them:</hi> Should we not count him a very Fool that ſhould go look for Figs on Thiſtles, or ſweet wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of a bitter Fountain? What if they ſhould ſay the Lord lives, that is a true ſaying to them which knows it in themſelves; but its a Lye to them who ſay it, and knows the contrary in them; but theſe Prieſts which Peach for Hire, cry Peace to men whilſt they put into their Mouthes, to the end their god may be ſupplyed, which cauſes and conſtrains their Mouthes to be open; but in caſe you deny to put into their Mouthes, then, <hi>Demetrius</hi> like, prepares War; crying out,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151357:8"/>we have a Law, and if you wont pay, we will make you pay: But by the way, what compulſive Law of man doth Chriſts Miniſters uſe, or were they to uſe? prove any ſuch thing in the Scriptures of Truth, that they were to compel any man to give to them: now, if God hath appointed no ſuch Maintenance by his Righteous Covenant and Law; Is it not ſtealth in his ſight, to compel and take that by mans Law, which God hath not appointed in his Law? Look about you Prieſts, for the Righteous Judge will ſit in Judgment, and to the Lambs Bar to give an account you muſt come, and then the twiſting Serpent will ſtand you in no ſtead, but all things will be laid bare before you, what eſteem you have had of your god, which is your Belly, for the ſerving of which, how have you yeelded unto the lying Spirit, and ſo like <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets perſwaded &amp; inſtigated many to go on in Perſecution, though to their deſtruction. Have you not told the Magiſtrates that the Quakers are Ring-Leaders of Faction, though you never come to their Meetings, nor never examined the cauſe why they diſſented from you; nor never heard that they went about to diſturb or moleſt any, of their outward injoyments, but barely becauſe they bore a faithfull Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt the twiſting twining Serpent, the great Enemy of mans Soul; which Spirit of Error your god cannot be ſerved without: ſo a great ſtir and ado you make, in being Inſtruments of caſting into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, haling and tearing away the Goods, and the like, from thoſe who lives in the Fear and Dread of the Lord God Almighty, and in peace with men, though in enmity with the Serpent, the Enemy of mans Soul: ſo the innocent blood which hath been ſhed in Naſty Holes, and Stinking Priſons, cries aloud unto the Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, who is Lord of all, who created all at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and can deſtroy all in the ſame; thoſe that be innocent, out of the revengefull ſpirit, have committed themſelves, and ſo cannot uſe any compulſive way, with Weapons that are Carnal, but in plain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration and Power of the Spirit of Truth, and their innocent Cauſe to the Judge of all they have committed, to be cleared in his will and time, who will aſſuredly do it. But further to clear that you are the Miniſters of Antichriſt, if, notwithſtanding what is declared, any yet be in doubt: Hearken what Chriſt ſaith to the Wicked, <hi>I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat: I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink: I was a ſtranger, and ye took me not in: naked, and ye cloathed me not: ſick, and in priſon, and viſited me not. Then ſhall they alſo anſwer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151357:8"/>him, ſaying, Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, or thirſty, or a ſtranger, or ſick, or in priſon, and did not miniſter unto thee? Then ſhall he anſwer them, ſaying, Verily I ſay unto you, inaſmuch as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me; and theſe ſhall go away into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing puniſhment,</hi> Matth. 25. In the ſame Chapter he ſhews the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mans love, and his reward; and how did they expreſs their love to Chriſt? Did they do it in ſpeaking great words of his Name? No, as you may read, they viſited his Brethren in their neceſſities: ſo mark by the way, there were Righteous men, and now are, though the Miniſters of Antichriſt for their gods ſake, would have all err and ſtray again from the Lords way; but the Pearl for which they have ſold all and bought, is of more value then ſo; but ſince Chriſt hath Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, are not they them which are led by the Spirit of Truth? and if people be given up to obey it, will it not lead them out of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Error? If ſo, then muſt they not depart from your wayes, who are in the Revengefull Spirit? Well then, ſince thoſe that are led by the Spirit are Sons of God, as the Scriptures of Truth declare, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and Heirs with Chriſt; for he that ſanctifieth, and them that are ſanctified are all of one, wherefore he is not aſhamed to call them Brethen: now ſince there is ſuch a unity between Chriſt and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, Shall it avail them any thing, who call upon Chriſt, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute ſo near Relations, as his Brethren? And ſince thoſe that viſited them not in their neceſſities, received ſuch condemnation, what will become of you? And you, Generation of wicked Doers, who have been the cauſe of the Impriſoning ſo many of Chriſts Relations, where ſeveral hundreds have laid down their lives for their faithfull Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt you, becauſe of your Adultery from the Lord, and his Worſhip, which is to be performed in Spirit and Truth, and have ſet up worſhips according to your own hearts Luſt: and becauſe of the Lords Patience, and Long-ſuffering, and great Mercy, how do you harden your hearts againſt Reproofs, and for good return evil, and ſo go on ſcoffing and mocking: well, though the Lord hath exerciſed a great deal of patience, its my belief, it will not laſt long; but he will execute Righteous Judgment, and plead the Cauſe of the Innocent, who hath committed all to him, with Praiſes and Glory from his own Works for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>The</hi> 21th <hi>day of the</hi> 11th <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1667.</date>
               <signed>Stephen Smith.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
